A Guide to the Sesame Club Records, 1932-2011
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Sesame Club Records 1932-2011
Thomas Balch Library
M 027
1.15 cu. ft.
Programs and attendance records of the Sesame Club, constituted "to study history, sociology, art and literature for the cultural improvement of the members."
Sesame Club
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Ann Thomas, Round Hill, VA.
Alternative Form Available
A CD of club constitutions and a CD of club history are filed in Box 4, Folder 6.
Accruals
2006.0157, 2012.0060
Historical Information
Late in 1932, nine women living in western Loudoun County, VA who were interested in enriching their lives established Sesame Club. The charter members were Martha McComb (19 Jun 1897-Mar 1972), Nan Cornwell (20 Jun 1897-Jan 1988), Louise Hawthorne (11 Dec 1898-Jul 1994), Alice Kerr Stehle, Evelyn Taylor Adams Litton (22 Oct 1904-9 Jan 1999), Margaret S. Taylor Chamblin (24 Mar 1901-10 Aug 1968), Sally R. Speer (nd), Julia Monroe (22 Aug 1892-Apr 1984), and Alice James (12 Jan 1887-20 May 1946). The club's constitution says, "The purpose of Sesame shall be to study history, sociology, art and literature for the cultural improvement of the members.' From 1932 to1952 Sesame's fiscal and program year was from September to September; in 1952 it was changed to begin in January.
The structure of the club is rather informal; the constitution provides that a nominating committee, appointed in September, propose a slate of officers consisting of president, vice-president, and secretary-treasurer who are elected in November to serve one year terms. The constitution also provides for the August appointment of a program committee. The committee is responsible for selecting a topic for the following year and assigning club members to prepare and present programs, which are given at each regular monthly meeting. Meetings are usually held in the home of one of the members. Ad hoc committees can and have been appointed as needed. Throughout the club's history program topics have included the history and culture of a number of countries, literature, music, fashion, art, and many other areas of interest.
Scope and Content
At the time of processing these records date from 1932 when the club was established and continue through 2006; it is an open collection - additions will be made periodically since the club is still active. The records of early years are incomplete, and from May 1943 until August 1944 the club did not meet. It reconvened in that month and has continued to meet regularly. Until 1947 programs were written and presented by members. Since that time, programs have been oral. Efforts have been made to obtain and preserve written copies of more recent programs and, when available, these are included in the files.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Sesame Club Records, 1932-2011 (M 027), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
CD-Rom capable computer
Related Material
None
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - A history of the club, list of members, list of program topics, financial records for 1980-1981
  - Club Constitutions
  - List of members for 1934; written programs on Russia presented during 1933-1934
  - Attendance record for 1935, written programs on the British Isles and Asia presented during 1935-1935
  - Attendance record for 1936, written programs on Scandinavia presented during 1935-1936
  - Written programs on Our Heritage presented during 1936-1937
  - Written programs on Asia (?)
  - Attendance records for 1938-1939; written programs on Modern Women
  - Written programs on Travel by Waterways of Europe presented during 1939-1940
  - Program booklet on Discovering South America; attendance and financial record for 1942-1943
  - Minutes for 1944
  - Attendance record, minutes, and written programs on Pacific World 1945-1946
  - Attendance record, financial record, and minutes for 1946-1947
  - Attendance record and minutes for 1948; one written program on China
  - Attendance record and minutes for 1948
  - One program on the topic of Plays and the Modern World
- (Box 2)
  - Program Booklets for 1950s; financial record for 1953
  - Program list for 1960; program booklets for 1961-1965
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1966
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1967
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1968
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1969
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1970
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1971
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1972
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1973
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1974
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1975
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1976
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1977
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1978
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1979
  - Attendance record, and minutes for 1980
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1981
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1982
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1983
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1984
  - Program booklet, attendance record, minutes for 1985; six written programs
  - Program booklet, attendance record, minutes for 1986; three written programs
  - Program booklet, attendance record, minutes for 1987; three written programs
  - Program booklet, attendance record, minutes for 1988; one
  - Program booklet, attendance record, minutes for 1989; six written programs
- (Box 3)
  - Attendance record and minutes for 1990; four written programs
  - Attendance record and minutes for 1991; four written programs
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1992
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1993
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1994
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1995, one written program
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1996
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1997
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1998
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 1999
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 2000
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 2001
  - Program booklet and minutes for 2002
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 2003, one written program
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 2004; four written programs
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 2005, Eight (8) written programs on Islam.
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 2006
- (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence
  - Miscellaneous written programs
  - Miscellaneous written programs
  - Obituaries and miscellaneous newspaper clippings about Sesame Club and its members
  - Extra program booklets
  - Two CDs--one of Club Constitutions and one of club history
  - Volume 1 of bound copies of published stories by Elizabeth (Betty) Stowe, Sesame member 1986-2004
  - Volume 2 of bound copies of published stories by Elizabeth (Betty) Stowe
- (Box 5)
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 2007, Eleven written programs
  - Program, pictures, notes from 75th Anniversary Luncheon, November 17, 1997; pictures of display at Thomas Balch Library (October, 2007) (folder 1 of 2)
  - Program, pictures, notes from 75th Anniversary Luncheon, November 17, 1997; pictures of display at Thomas Balch Library (October, 2007) (folder 2 of 2)
  - Program booklet, attendance record, and minutes for 2008, nine written programs
  - Program booklet, attendance record, minutes for 2009. Nine (9) written programs on Ancient Civilizations.
  - Program booklet, attendance record, minutes for 2010. Eight (8 ) written programs on Ethobotany.
  - Program booklet, minutes for 2011, written programs for "Our Journey Through Hallowed Ground"